William Edward Riley Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Edward Riley Papers 1941-1948
MSS14944
Riley, William Edward, 1897-
800 items
5 containers
2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Marine Corps officer. Correspondence, operation plans and reports, memoranda, notes, maps, photographs, and other papers relating to Riley’s World War II service on the staff of Admiral William Frederick Halsey, commander of South Pacific Area and commander in chief of the United States Navy 3rd Fleet; invasions of the Philippines and Ulithi (Micronesia); and United States Marine Corps and United States Navy demobilization efforts after the war.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Forrestal, James, 1892-1949.; Halsey, William F. (William Frederick), 1882-1959.; Kinkaid, Thomas C. (Thomas Cassin), 1888-1972.; Leahy, William D.; Riley, William Edward, 1897-1970.; Royall, Kenneth C. (Kenneth Claiborne), 1894-1971.
Organizations
United States. Marine Corps--Demobilization.; United States. Marine Corps--Officers.; United States. Navy--Demobilization.; United States. Navy. Fleet, 3rd.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Micronesia.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--South Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.
Places
Ulithi (Micronesia)
Occupations
Marine Corps officers.
Provenance
The papers of William Edward Riley, Marine Corps officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1968. An addition was received from the Naval Historical Foundation in 1976. The deposit was converted to a gift in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Edward Riley are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Edward Riley (1897-1970) span the years 1941-1948 and consist of correspondence, memoranda, operation plans, reports, speeches and speech material, maps, photographs, notes, printed matter, and other material. The papers relate to Riley's World War II service on the staff of Admiral William Frederick Halsey, commander of South Pacific Area and commander in chief of the U.S. Navy 3rd Fleet; invasions of the Philippines and Ulithi (Micronesia); and U.S. Marine Corps and U.S. Navy demobilization efforts after the war. Also included are copies of speeches by James Forrestal, William Frederick Halsey, Thomas Cassin Kinkaid, William D. Leahy, and Kenneth Claiborne Royall.
Arrangement of the Papers
The papers are organized into a subject file, arranged alphabetically by name of person, topic, or type of material, and a miscellany file, arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - Armed services, unification, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Demobilization notebook, 1944-1947, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hull, Cordell, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Leyete operations, Philippine Islands, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Maps (Box 1)
    - Australia, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Bismarck Archipelago and Solomon Islands, 1943, undated (Box 1)
    - Central Pacific and Philippine Islands, 1944, undated (Box 1)
    - Germany, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Japan, 1944, undated (Box 1)
    - New Calédone, undated (Box 1)
    - New Guinea, undated (Box 1)
    - Southeast Asia, 1944, undated (Box 2)
    - Southwest Pacific area, undated (Box 2)
    - Yokohama, port, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Marine Corps tables of organization, deviations, 1945 (Box 2)
  - New Jersey (battleship), action reports, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Prisoner of war interrogation report, 1945 (Box 2)
  - South Pacific operations, 1942-1944, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Third Fleet, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Ulithi Islands, 1944 (Box 2)
  - United States Atlantic Fleet, organization of, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Yap Islands, 1944 (Box 2)
- Miscellany (Box 3)
  - Article, "Why We Lost," by a German commander, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, South Pacific forces, 1944, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed matter (Box 3)
    - 1941-1944, (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1945, (9 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1945, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1946-1947, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Speech file (Box 5)
    - Defensive combat, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Forrestal, James, Victory Day statement, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Halsey, William Frederick, duties of a theater commander, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - Kinkaid, Thomas C., Victory in Japan Day celebration, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Leahy, William D., 1946 (Box 5)
    - Postwar military establishment and manpower problems, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Royall, Kenneth C., 1947 (Box 5)